Guide to the Nathan Sinai Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Nathan Sinai papers
1912-1966
MS 760
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, speeches, writings, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and research files documenting Nathan Sinai's career as a professor of public health at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor and his many posts on national and international health organizations. Included also are research data concerning costs of medical care in three cities in the United States in 1929 compiled by the Committee on the Costs of Medical Care, material on medical relief in Essex County, Ontario, and studies and reports on medical economics in Michigan (1933-1948). Also papers on the Twentieth Century Fund, the World Health Organization and on health benefits for the UAW-CIO in 1949. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical and Health Policy Collection.
Sinai, Nathan, 1894-1977
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nathan Sinai, 1974.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Newspaper Clippings and Scrapbooks. III. Addresses and Writings. IV. Subject File.
Scope and Contents
The Nathan Sinai Papers (3 storage cartons) have been divided into four general series. Within each series, the material has been very roughly arranged. Most of the material is still in the original folders, but some loose material has been put in new folders. The four series are:
I. CORRESPONDENCE (5 folders)
II. NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS AND SCRAPBOOKS (3/4 carton)
III. ADDRESSES AND WRITINGS (1 carton)
IV. SUBJECT FILE (1 carton)
The first series, CORRESPONDENCE, contains only several letters that were found among other material in the Papers.
NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS AND SCRAPBOOKS, the second series, contains magazine and newspaper clippings about Sinai and his work and other public health topics. There are also many reviews of Sinai's books and articles. Also included in this series are programs and schedules from numerous conventions, dinners, and meetings that Sinai attended or addressed. Most of the material found in this section was originally in scrapbooks, but since much of it had become detached, it has been removed and placed in folders.
The third series, ADDRESSES AND WRITINGS, contains manuscripts, transcripts, and some printed copies of speeches and articles by Sinai. These are arranged chronologically.
Some writings by Sinai are also contained in the fourth series, the SUBJECT FILE. The material in this series has been roughly grouped together by subject. For example, material relating to Sinai's work on the Committee on Medical Economics of the Michigan State Medical Society has been filed together.
The following list is of folder titles in each series and each carton. The folders are not numbered, but they are in the following order.
Box number corresponds with carton number.
Biographical / Historical
Nathan Sinai: foundation official; D.V.M., San Francisco College, 1915; M.S. in Public Health, University of Michigan, 1924, Dr. P.H., 1926; director, Division of Sanitation, Stockton, 1916-1921; health officer, Stockton, 1921-1923; instructor, hygiene and public health, University of Michigan, 1924-1927, assistant professor, 1927-1929, associate professor, 1929-1932, professor, 1932-1964, professor emeritus, 1964-.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Medical care, Cost of; Medical economics; Medicine; Public health; Essex (Ont.: County); Michigan; Educators; Health services administrators; Health-officers; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Burnell, Max Ronald, 1893-1959; Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959; Sinai, Nathan, 1894-1977; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America
- CORRESPONDENCE, Series I
  - Burnell, Max R. (1), 1950 (Box 1)
  - Donovan, Brigadier General William (3), 1944 (Box 1)
  - Easlick, Kenneth A. (1), 1942 (Box 1)
  - Life Magazine (1), 1945 (Box 1)
  - McMahon, James (1), 1912 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania State Dental Society (1), 1931 (Box 1)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Public Health Service (2), 1968 (Box 1)
  - Warren, Earl (1), 1947 (Box 1)
  - Western Canada Dental Society (1), 1931 (Box 1)
- NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS AND SCRAPBOOKS, Series II
  - Programs and schedules from conventions, dinners, meetings, 1931-1946, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Commencement program and magazines from Sinai's high school, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1921, 1928, 1930-1935, 1937-1951, undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper parody promoting sanitary privies (published by USPHS and WPA) (Box 1)
  - Misc. (Box 1)
- ADDRESSES AND WRITINGS, Series III
  - "The Improvement of the Sanitary Personnel,", 1924 (Box 2)
  - "The Costs of Medical Care to 4,560 Families: Preliminary Report" by N. Sinai and M. Klem, 1930 (Box 2)
  - "National Health Insurance in England,", 1930 (Box 2)
  - "Costs of Medical Care,", 1931 (Box 2)
  - "The Trend of Medicine" (alternate version of "Costs of Medical Care"), 1931 (Box 2)
  - "Our System of Medical Care" (early version of "Costs of Medical Care"?), 1931 (Box 2)
  - "The Medical Insurance Situation in the United States,", 1931 (Box 2)
  - "The Way of Health Insurance,", 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - "In Defence of Doctor Dewey,", 1932 (Box 2)
  - "Social Evolution in Medicine and Dentistry,", 1932 (Box 2)
  - "Health Insurance Movement,", 1932 (Box 2)
  - "Organization and Administration of Public Health,", 1933 (Box 2)
  - "The Distribution of Medical Service,", 1933 (Box 2)
  - "Medical and Dental Economics,", 1934 (Box 2)
  - "Current History in Medicine and Dentistry,", 1935 (Box 2)
  - "Mutual Health Service,", 1935 (Box 2)
  - Public health organization in Michigan, 1935 (Box 2)
  - "Health Insurance,", 1935 (Box 2)
  - "Social Security: The Problem of Sickness,", 1935 (Box 2)
  - "Let Us Have Facts,", 1935 (Box 2)
  - "Medical and Dental Relief: Policies and Results,", 1936 (Box 2)
  - "Medical Relief in Michigan" by N. Sinai, M.F. Hall, V. M. Hoge, and M. Steep (Box 2)
  - "Health as a National Asset,", 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - "The Need for a National Health Program,", 1938 (Box 2)
  - Planning for Health Needs: A Résumé of National and Community Efforts in "Curriculum Problems in Physical Education, School Health and Recreation,", 1938 (Box 2)
  - "People Are Alike" (rough draft and notes), 1938 (Box 2)
  - "Talks on Medical Care Before the Cincinnati Medical Society,", 1939 (Box 2)
  - "The Present Situation Regarding the Adequacy of Medical Care in the United States,", 1939 (Box 2)
  - "The Medical Economic Scene,", 1939 (Box 2)
  - "Systems of Prepayment for Medical Care Operated by Physicians,", 1940 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan compared to Harvard and Johns Hopkins, 1940 (Box 2)
  - "Public Health and Public Medical Service" by N. Sinai, C. Mann, A. Lough, A. M. Beeuwkes, 1940 (Box 2)
  - "Group Purchase of Medical Care and Hospitalization,", 1940 (Box 2)
  - "Singapore Calling,", 1940 (Box 2)
  - "All-Out Sacrifice,", 1941 (Box 2)
  - "Where Is Dentistry Going in Public Health?,", 1941 (Box 2)
  - "Physical Fitness and the Draft,", 1941 (Box 2)
  - "But Health Insurance Is Different,", 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - "Medical Service Plans,", 1942 (Box 2)
  - "Needed: A Realistic Health Plan,", 1942 (Box 2)
  - "Proposed Program for Studies of Social Security in Latin America,", 1942 (Box 2)
  - Report of "Adult Health Panel Discussion" of Health for Victory Conference, 1942 (Box 2)
  - "Are Local Health and Medical Services a Federal Problem?" ("Town Meeting" radio broadcast), 1943 (Box 2)
  - "Social Movement with Respect to Medical Care,", 1943 (Box 2)
  - "Current Trends in Medical Services,", 1943 (Box 2)
  - "The Present Status of Health Insurance in the United States,", 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - "Content and Administration of a Medical Care Program,", 1944 (Box 2)
  - "Health Economics,", 1944 (Box 2)
  - Medical economics and health insurance, 1945 (Box 2)
  - "The Administration of Prepaid Medical Care,", 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Organization for Medical Care,", 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Health Insurance Plans,", 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Ability of Population to Pay for Dental Service,", 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Public Health Economics" (series of lectures), 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Public Health Organization and Administration, Richmond, Va." by N. Sinai and A. Wilson, 1945 (Box 2)
  - "Medical Economics,", 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - "The Movement in Medical Economics,", 1946 (Box 2)
  - "Proposed Health Legislation,", 1946 (Box 2)
  - "Health Economics - Teaching Content and Methods,", 1946 (Box 2)
  - "Changing Issues in Health Economics,", 1946 (Box 2)
  - "The Training of Administrative Personnel and Research in Public Health Economics,", 1946 (Box 2)
  - "Experience and Lessons from Emergency Maternity and Infant Care,", 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - "Plantation Health Services - Analysis and Recommendations" by N. Sinai and C. Peterson, 1947 (Box 2)
  - "Three Fiscal Years in Health Economics,", 1948 (Box 2)
  - "EMIC - Emergency Maternity and Infant Care,", 1948 (Box 2)
  - "The Problems of Medical and Dental Care,", undated (Box 2)
  - "The March of Public Health,", undated (Box 2)
  - "What Is Public Health?" by G. Vida, 1940 (Box 2)
  - "Sickness Insurance Problems in the United States" (no author listed), undated (Box 2)
  - List of published writings by Sinai (compiled 1949 Sep) (Box 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, Series IV
  - California, City of Stockton Health Dept
    - "Annual Report for 1922,", 1923 (Box 3)
  - The Committee on the Costs of Medical Care
    - Letter requesting data, undated (Box 3)
    - A Survey of the Medical Facilities of the City of Philadelphia: 1929 by N. Sinai and A. B. Mills, 1931 (Box 3)
    - A Study of Physicians and Dentists in Detroit: 1929 by N. Sinai and A. B. Mills, 1931 (Box 3)
    - A Survey of the Medical Facilities of San Joaquin County, California: 1929 by N. Sinai, 1931 (Box 3)
    - "Errata" (statement by I. S. Falk, M. Klem, and N. Sinai in response to criticism of Committee statistics), 1933? (Box 3)
  - Essex County Medical Economic Research
    - "Medical Relief and Related Problems,", 1936 (Box 3)
    - Medical Relief Administration: the Experience in Essex County, Ontario, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Medical Relief Administration: Final Report of Experience in Essex County, Ontario by N. Sinai, M. F. Hall, and R. E. Holmes, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State health departments
    - "Gearing Our Public Health Programs To Meet Wartime Conditions" (reports of panel discussion), 1942 (Box 3)
    - "Report of the Board of Health on the Coordination of City and County Health Activities,", 1942 (Box 3)
    - Notes and papers re: hospitalization rates of two Michigan counties, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Care of the indigent in Washtenaw County, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State Medical Society (Committee on Medical Economics)
    - Papers, re: study of postgraduate medical education needs, 1933, undated (Box 3)
    - "Postgraduate Medicine for General Practitioners" (report of Committee), 1935 (Box 3)
    - Papers re: study of medical economics and facilities, 1931, undated (Box 3)
    - "Report of the Committee on Survey of Medical services and Health Agencies,", 1933 (Box 3)
    - "Report of the Committee on Survey of Medical Services and Health Agencies,", 1933 (Box 3)
    - Report of Committee on Medical Economics presenting Mutual Health Service plan, 1933 (Box 3)
    - Proposed program for Michigan Committee on Medical Economics, 1933 (Box 3)
    - "Luce-Sinai Report to the Executive Committee of the Michigan State Medical Society,", 1934 (Box 3)
    - "Report of the Committee on Medical Economics,", 1934 (Box 3)
    - "The Detroit Plan of Medical Participation,", 1934 (Box 3)
    - Three resolutions re: Mutual Health Service, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Memorandum to Committee on Medical Economics re: income limits, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Papers re: Medical Security Corporation of Michigan, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Papers re: Mutual Health Service, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Report to the Council of the Michigan State Dental Society, 1935 (Box 3)
    - Summary of medical relief in 10 counties, Michigan, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Michigan, University of
    - Tentative report to the University Council on physical education, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Notes and papers re: health insurance, undated (Box 3)
    - Notes and papers re: organization and planning of school of public health, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Papers re: school of public health, 1941-1942, 1946-1947, 1949 (Box 3)
    - "Proceedings of Inservice Training Course on Public Health Statistics for Health Directors and Public Health Statisticians,", 1948 (Box 3)
    - Papers re: University of Michigan employee benefit plan, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Twentieth Century Fund, Inc.
    - Annual Reports,", 1933-1934 (Box 3)
    - Report on medical economics for Twentieth Century Fund, 1935 (Box 3)
  - UAW-CIO
    - Papers re: health benefits for UAW-CIO workers, 1949 (Box 3)
  - World Health Organization
    - Copy of letter from John Foster Dulles to Richard M. Nixon re: WHO appropriation, 1955 (Box 3)
    - American Review of World Health,", 1966 (Box 3)
    - Transcript of speech on Australia and WHO (no author listed), undated (Box 3)